welcome to meditating with john riveting
live stream every weekday morning at 9
30 a.m eastern time
with mondays alternating between a new
lesson dharma day which happened
yesterday
and a review of the whole ecology of
practices in pie a day
for previous lessons and said see the
description if you're joining us for the
first time you know welcome
i strongly recommend you go to the links
do lesson one
and then do one or two lessons every
every week and you'll
soon catch up with us and
you'll be properly homed within the
course and the segment
but ask you all to please uh like this
video stream to
increase its visibility on the youtube
algorithm and help as many people as i
possibly can
at the end of every session there is a q
a period
please limit your questions to uh
anything from the entire ecology
practices
um the stuff we've already done
in the eastern stream or the stuff we're
doing now from the western stream
i will give priority for a while two
questions
that are connected with the wisdom of
hypatia because
we need to be doing uh we need to be
tending to that material in a more
socratic fashion but
we will get the questions beyond the
wisdom of hypatia
as much as possible if you have more
encompassing questions
please come to the live stream
general q a every third friday of the
month at 3 pm
eastern time it on youtube it will be
august the 21st of this month
okay so tomorrow i will review and
extend a bit what we learned on monday
and then i will do a review and
extension again on friday
but uh for today and thursday
let's concentrate on getting a good sit
in and having some
uh extended time for answering some
questions
all right so please get yourself in
position
set your phones up do not disturb and we
will begin with some chanting
and then we'll go into a silence so
we'll all begin uh when i say
i'll begin
begin
[Music]
one
on
can you silence it
uh
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you've
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communicates
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay so let's answer some questions
akarima cynthia clayton karima always
good to hear from you and thank you for
the comments you put on the videos
um should we read the next two chapters
i recommend not
i recommend re-reading and studying
um the chapters that are uh setting up
the basic practice
like the self-examination uh what what
we mean by
philosophy in this context what i what i
tend to call philia sophia
and especially um all of this the
materials surrounding epicureanism so
really sink into it
um so try to go quite intense
lean deep into it reviewing it and
studying it
doing the practices we're going to do it
a little bit faster than mcclellan
recommends he recommends you sort of
as a nine month course we're going to do
a little bit faster than that
but i do recommend we we stick with you
know at least
um we stick to epicureanism
for at least a couple of weeks and then
we'll move into stoicism
we'll probably be there a little bit
longer and the neoplatonism will be
there
even longer because of course it's
cumulative
in that manner next is dimitar
you've mentioned trying tdcs and
meditation have you also tried being in
a sense you get prevention tank and
meditation
is there any research on the effects of
set to deprivation tanks
meditation uh no i have not done that
um my mineers actually prevents me from
using something like a sensory
deprivation
tank my good friend and colleague
anderson todd is very interested in that
and he might be someone to contact
whether or not there is information and
research
on the integration of sensory
deprivation tanks and meditation you
wouldn't of course you couldn't it's too
expensive i imagine
you wouldn't want to make it a regular
part of
the practice it's going to get dependent
on that etc
but it might be something that gets
incorporated into a powerful ritual
as a way of bringing about a very
significant
state of consciousness that could be
integrated
into the aspiration to wisdom
so that's what i recommend there i don't
know very much
um so i recommend
if you can his name is anderson todd
he's done talks with me and voices
for making is his own channel uh opening
up soon i believe it's called opus
um and so you might want to reach out to
him
uh he's a colleague like at uft and he's
a dear friend of mine
lynn slater hi lynn good to uh hear from
you
observation i find savoring comes
naturally
to me but the long-term short-term issue
is much more difficult
yeah but thank you for sharing that len
observation that's the case so the
saving on its own
uh needs to be coupled uh to the
maximization
uh to the uh right
the application i think that's the right
word the application
of the maxims to maximize our frame
widening
uh because the research shows um that
this is you need to
bring in to symbolically make to put
together within the same framing
your current self your future self
and your current desire your long term
desire and right that is where you can
start to make
the evaluation so when you're making
these evaluations the point of the
savoring
is to give you a phenomenological
sense a touchstone
for what it's like to be
satisfying a and prioritizing
a desire that
is important rather than merely intense
and that has long-term
sustainability it's meant to be so you
could
you could sort of say this desire
doesn't
satisfy this desire doesn't feel very
close
to what it's like to enjoy
and savor pure being so it's designed to
give you a phenomenological
standard that is meant to be integrated
with the conceptual
reflection when you're doing the
maximization and applying the principle
so you can think of it almost as higher
order savory the point of
the of the savoring practice
is to open up and to have you have a
more phenomenological experience
of this type of desire as a touchstone
and its satisfaction this type of
pleasure because that's what i should be
saying
and then that's supposed to be
integrated with the
principles that are coming out of the
maximization
to give you the best possible
discernment
about what pleasures you should be
orienting to
and that should hopefully help uh
get you into uh being able to open up to
the long term
i don't think it's sufficient uh
remember
that epicureanism is primary school
stoicism is high school
and neoplatonism is university and so uh
we are going to add on significantly uh
to epicureanism within stoicism for how
to
properly orient uh towards
the long term and the deeper etc
so i hope that's helpful to you but then
gao good to see you ben
and struggling against sleepiness i
sometimes intentionally take a few deep
breaths sit more erect and imagine a
line pulling me up from the top of my
head is that okay yes
uh that is actually something that
especially that line pulling you like
this
that is something that you um
are recommended to i'm sorry that one is
recommended to do within tai chi chuan
when you're standing at wuji
i didn't mention it because i tend to
find that when i do that people get all
stiff
um but if it's coming to you naturally
if it's a way if you can do that without
losing suppleness
right and you just but doing that that's
a way of triggering
that kind of rootedness uh that's um
within tai chi chuan so i think that's a
good practice to do
uh lisa van wyk uh welcome lizzle you're
constantly in the sangha and making
edifying and helpful comments and
interaction
your presence is much appreciated
observation this weekend i saw a close
friend of mine i haven't seen
uh since lockdown joining the senior
you're different she said
ah a few hours into this visit
more restful i couldn't help thinking of
john saying that the best way to know
that the meditation is working is when
we notice
when others know this changes in you
very motivated thank you for sharing
that
that will start to happen to you more
often i would predict
in other people and it's going to happen
to all of us at some point
if you um if you maintain your
friendship to the way
then this starts to occur more and more
and it is very motivating
and it's encouraging
in a way in which all of your self
affirmations can never be
encouraging and i think as i said
that's ultimately the touchstone if you
that you should
look to to see if you're on the path
kelly myers welcome kelly
the intentions and conceptual framing of
the past night meta are lost to me in
prajna however
would you recommend i work to bring them
back or just surrender to savor
the felt sex yes move beyond the
conceptualizations the conceptually
this is going to be really apparent when
we move to the neoplatonic
right uh grove so
if you get to prajna and you just have
that
felt sense and it might be beyond
conceptualization
stay with that savor it that that's
right
that's that's what you want to do
because eventually you want to move from
you want to move beyond the subject
object duality of thinking
this is one of platinus's main arguments
all thinking even our highest
conceptions
have us in a subject object
differentiation and so we
we move we go trans-conceptual not
sub-conceptual
we're going to talk about distinguishing
those right there right the trans-egoic
and the pre-egoic the trans-conceptual
the pre-conceptual right so you
can go trans-conceptual when you're in
the state of prajna
so just do what you said savor the felt
sense
um tasha kellogg asks
which book is being read i am new here
um i'll go get it jason can you bring it
to me please actually
okay so the book we're using is called
the wisdom of hypatia
by milk kleinen we have read up to page
70.
i believe it's the first is it the first
three chapters of the first four
chapters
uh let me see
the first four chapters so that's what
i'm going to do
i strongly recommend you get another
book uh called what is ancient
philosophy
by pierre haddow hedo is spelled h
a d o t but this is the mandatory book
uh the strongly recommended book to
accompany it
is what is ancient philosophy by pierre
hadou
keisha kellogg hello kisha oh no sorry
that was keisha's question
i misread
hi stan it's good to hear from you again
was it through part two one was supposed
to read
um you read all the way up to part one
uh all the way up to part seven
um oh sorry all the way up to what's
called part three my mistake
you're right i'm misleading you guys i
apologize um
the way he devises this book up is a
little bit uh a little bit
confusing to me but we're reading all
the way
up to part three but
it's what he calls the first degree of
wisdom so that's the confusion
so i'm thinking of the first degree
that whole section that he calls the
first degree he calls it
uh part three of the book and it's up to
page 70
in the pagination so
finish part one sorry
i keep doing it finish the first degree
of wisdom
finish up two part three but don't start
part three
so i hope that answers your question uh
el reeve
what is the purpose of meditation
the purpose of meditation is
something that
changes as you meditate because
it is only something that can be
realized as you
undergo transformation it's like asking
what's the purpose of being in a
friendship
initially what draws you in is a set of
features in the person
but then you are changed and you see
deeper features in the person
and then you ask you made that point and
say well why am i on this trajectory in
this friendship
and what it is is i'm coming into a
fullness of being
my friend helps me to overcome patterns
of self-deception
this is how a friend is different than a
buddy right aristotle talked about
uh friendship is like realizing that
there's one soul
and one self in two bodies um
my friend helps me to overcome
self-deception uh my
my friend is there to support me when
fate
hammers at me my friend is there to help
me to
transcend and grow beyond myself to see
things
to get into right relationship with
other people
to get into a right relationship with
myself and the world this is what deep
friendship is and we're going to be
talking about this
uh as the core of epicureanism the point
the purpose of meditation is to enter
into this
kind of deep friendship with yourself
that grows and the purpose changes and
grows like
the purpose of friendship because you're
coming into right relationship you're
overcoming self-deception
you're affording self-transcending
you're moving into a depth of being
being yourself being with others and
being in the world
it's ultimately therefore in that sense
about the cultivation
of wisdom matthew mccready
welcome matthew observation in the
rooting phase i sometimes feel like my
awareness
is blocked from going to the next part
of my body about what feels like a stone
or a wall
and i have to go around it yes yes
matthew
so to decide how long you're going to
stay there ahead of time for each
and then you often we will hit these i
still hit it
and i've been doing this for what almost
30 years
and that's what i mean about body armor
michael washburn's book
called the ego on the dynamic ground i
recommend reading it especially the
second edition
michael washburn w-h-w-a-s-h-b-u-r-n
michael washburn
the ego and the dynamic crowd i think
this is one of the best books
um in transpersonal psychology i think
washburn is in such sense uh
um a more psychologically astute
uh transpersonal psychologist than
wilbur but anyways
uh washburn's notion of body armor uh
that we will we all possess ways
in which we and levine levines didn't
work on this right now but
how the body remembers trauma um
and so that is not something you should
try to smash
right it's that that that is something
that has to be
in friendship and virtuous friendship
slowly
eroded and washed away with persistent
perspicacious but also very kind
like awareness and so it's something
that
you you if you'll allow me a bit of a
metaphor
that is caressed away it is not
something that is smashed or broken away
and um so be patient with yourself and
what you're doing is exactly right
don't devote some time to it but then
you just need to go around it
but also don't be disappointed that it's
you're going to be with us for a long
time and
it would be gentle and
there will there will be a change there
will be a change
um so this is trump
are both of these questions from james
the one we don't have
with the second questions from okay so
the first question
sorry the next question is from james uh
luffler hi james
what is the best way to get in touch
with john um
so the best way to get in touch with me
sorry to refer to myself in the third
person um
uh what i'm going i think what i should
do is i'm going to talk to amar
we're setting up we're trying to set up
a an email for uh
you know this community and we're going
to get that set up and then i'll post
that
uh to these videos so that people can
get in touch with me
um it's important
for me to say that um
i have to be i have to have to be very
careful in the sense of caution but also
full of care
so both senses to be very careful about
my time
there's lots of people sorry this i
don't mean to sound self-aggrandized
but there are lots of people who want to
talk to me and communicate with me
and i have to i have to be i have to be
very careful with this
um so um i i will
a communication channel will be set up
but
i also need people to be patient
and to be understanding about it i'm
pleased
it's this is i'm finding this
i'm finding this challenging it's a
challenge i want to meet it's a
challenge
i aspire to meeting meeting honorably
and in virtue but it is a challenge and
i'm still
trying to calibrate to it so
a communication channel will be made
available but please
i ask for people to use it judiciously
patiently and with understanding
so last question is unnamed hi john how
would you combine meditating on symbols
for
virtue with the memory palace technique
and lectio divina
for important writings on them um
so i'm gonna i'm gonna i'm gonna
hold off on answering that question
because that is going to come
into central prominence when we get to
the grove when we're doing neoplatonism
and when we're talking about
theergia when we're talking about theory
just so we're definitely going to come
back
to that and the kinds of practices
around that
and that's where we're going to see
important connections to
um aspects of jung
and corban and um people like that
um so you might want to take a look at
um the episodes
i forget which ones are it's anyways the
last four episodes of awakening for the
meeting crisis when i talk about
the prophets at the meeting crisis
because they talked about young and
corvette i also talk about barfield and
and they all sort of belong together in
this
deep discussion about um
the appropriate and responsible relating
to
and through symbols
so i want to thank you all for joining
and for the excellent questions
i encourage you to keep practicing i
encourage you to share both observations
and
questions remember the wisdom of hypatia
i'm going to give you practices
um and we're and i talked with brett and
matt and we're going to
have a place on the discord server for
doing the group practices
i thank them for that um but uh
i do need you guys to be to be more
socratic about this ask me
questions about what you're reading or
the practice um
so i can so i can
hopefully guide you as helpfully as
possible
i want to thank jason my beloved son
who's been doing
everything today and doing a fantastic
job
it's it's it's uh it's a truly wonderful
thing
when your son becomes one of your best
friends
i want to thank all of you
for your supporting of each other as
well
i don't do that as often as i should but
i read the comments i always read the
comments in the chat
after i see so many of you helping each
other
and edifying each other and encouraging
each other
and i just want to encourage that thank
you so much please subscribe to this
channel to be notified of the next video
you'll find links to the lecture series
awakening for the
meeting crisis you'll find links to the
diologos
series where i try to exemplify the
dialectic it's going to be important
to neoplatonism there's also a new
series coming
there's untangling the world not of
consciousness that
it's doing with greg henry kiss uh there
is
a leader what's coming is uh a a lecture
series on the nature of the self
and of course um the major one
uh that uh it is coming that's going to
be
sort of the same scope and scale as
awakening for the meaning crisis is
after socrates
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series
please join the discord servers to chat
with other to do the moving practice
to do extra meditation extra sitting and
more and
more most importantly right now and not
most importantly
most currently that's the word i wanted
to say uh
join the discord server uh so that
you'll be able to do these group
practices
uh like philosophical companionship
and then down the road dialectic into
the logos etc
we're doing this every weekday morning
at 9 30 eastern time
please follow me on twitter if you're
not opposed to it in principle
for the fastest updates
please remember that on the discord
server um every second monday
i do a live q a i did one yesterday but
i also do one
next week to catch up please remember
that continuity of practice is more
important than sheer quantity of
practice
don't hold yourself to a standard of
harsh perfection hold yourself to a
standard of virtuous friendship
because there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body there is no
friend no ally no true companion on the
path
better than your own mind and body be
lamps unto yourselves into each other
take good care everyone i'll see you
tomorrow
you